<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>HHormones &#8211; Harmonious-Hormones</title>
	<atom:link href="/author/hhormones/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 09:28:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Fibroids</title>
		<link>/fibroids/</link>
					<comments>/fibroids/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[HHormones]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 10:31:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Harmonious Hormones: Learn & Flow]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=318</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Intro Fibroids are benign growths that are found in the uterus. They are most common in women between the ages of 25 to 50 and black women. Fibroids  affect up to 80% of women during their lifetime. I’ve personally experienced fibroids (you can read my story [here]) and I had to undergo a myomectomy to [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/uterine-fibroids-5-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-319" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/uterine-fibroids-5-1024x683.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/uterine-fibroids-5-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/uterine-fibroids-5-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/uterine-fibroids-5.jpg 1153w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Intro</h2>



<p>Fibroids are benign growths that are found in the uterus. They are most common in women between the ages of 25 to 50 and black women. Fibroids  affect up to 80% of women during their lifetime. I’ve personally experienced fibroids (you can read my story [<a href="/my-story/" data-type="post" data-id="107">here</a>]) and I had to undergo a myomectomy to remove them. In this post, I will explore what causes fibroids, symptoms, treatment options, and my thoughts on what needs to change in women’s healthcare. If you are dealing with fibroids, know that I do understand fully what you are going through and I hope this post  gives you clarity and support.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What Causes Fibroids?</h2>



<p>The exact issue is still unknown, but research and medical evidence show that hormones, genes, and lifestyle play a significant role. Let’s explore all these factors one by one.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Hormonal Imbalance</h2>



<p>If your hormones are imbalanced (I have discussed this <a href="/hormonal-imbalance/" data-type="post" data-id="301">link </a>here), the estrogen level is high relative to progesterone, causing estrogen dominance. This usually occurs when the liver isn’t detoxing estrogen well, high body fat and exposure to synthetic estrogens (These are manmade substances that mimic estrogen). These synthetic estrogens are in phthalates and other chemicals like BPA. They are usually found in plastics, cosmetic products, pesticides and herbicides, flame retardants, dioxins, and heavy metals(present in furniture, electronics, industrial waste, and polluted water).</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Progesterone</h2>



<p>If progesterone hormone levels are high, they promote and enlarge the fibroids. This happens when the fibroids are already present in the uterus. In other words, it acts like fertilizer.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Vitamin D Deficiency</h2>



<p>Lack of vitamin D is also linked to fibroid development because it helps regulate cell growth and reduce inflammation. Studies show women with low vitamin D levels are more likely to develop fibroids. This deficiency is common in Black women due to melanin reducing vitamin D production from sunlight.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Genetic Links</h2>



<p>Do women in your family have it? Then the likelihood of you having it is high, and certain genetic mutations can lead to faster fibroid growth.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Lifestyle Factors and Environmental Exposure</h2>



<p>How you eat and workout. If it&#8217;s unhealthy  you are prone to get it and promote their growth. For a healthy lifestyle, I have tips in these posts here on <a href="/cycle-and-diet/" data-type="post" data-id="312">diet </a>and <a href="/cycle-and-workouts/" data-type="post" data-id="307">workout</a>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Common Symptoms of Fibroids</h2>



<p>Symptoms of fibroids are usually heavy painful periods with clots, irregular periods , bloating, constipation, pelvic pressure, frequent urination, pain during sex, spotting during periods, and a pregnant belly when you haven’t conceived. If you experience these symptoms, please book an appointment with your gynecologist who will do a scan and confirm the presence of fibroids.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Diagnosed With Fibroids &#8211; What Next?</h2>



<p>Things you need to consider are the size, number (that is, how many are they), location, and impact. Where the fibroids are located affects your uterus, other organs, and symptoms. Check below size chart and location table to understand deeper.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="651" height="977" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/image.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-320" style="width:348px;height:auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/image.jpg 651w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/image-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 651px) 100vw, 651px" /></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Types of Fibroids by Location</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table class="has-fixed-layout"><thead><tr><td><strong>Type</strong></td><td><strong>Where It Grows</strong></td><td><strong>Symptoms / Impact</strong></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><strong>Intramural</strong></td><td>Inside the <strong>uterine wall</strong> (muscle)</td><td>Most common. Heavy bleeding, pain, pressure</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Submucosal</strong></td><td>Just <strong>under the lining</strong> of the uterus (endometrium)</td><td>Worst for bleeding and <strong>infertility</strong> may cause miscarriages</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Subserosal</strong></td><td>On the <strong>outer wall</strong> of the uterus</td><td>May press on bladder or bowels. Bloating, frequent urination, constipation</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Pedunculated</strong></td><td>Hanging on a <strong>stalk</strong> outside or inside the uterus</td><td>Can twist and cause sharp pain</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Cervical</strong></td><td>In or near the <strong>cervix</strong></td><td>May cause bleeding after sex or block vaginal delivery</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Intracavitary</strong></td><td>Inside the <strong>uterine cavity</strong></td><td>It affects fertility, implantation, and causes cramping and spotting</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Treatment Options Available</h2>



<p>A gynecologist will likely recommend a myomectomy, which is fibroid removal surgery if you have large multiple fibroids. If this is the case, don’t be scared because this is a healing option too. . As much as you might think it&#8217;s extreme, it&#8217;s all about improving your health. It is important to note even after the myomectomy the fibroids can recur. The other way is the UFE (Uterine Fibroid Embolization). This is non-surgical and less invasive way for shrinking them. What is done is that a radiologist blocks blood flow to fibroids and a warning is that it may not be ideal if you want to get pregnant.</p>



<p>Another treatment option is hormonal therapy where you can be put on birth control depending on which hormone is high, estrogen or progesterone. So, the aim of this is to shrink the sizes of fibroids. It’s not a permanent solution. You can also opt for natural supplements that can help balance the hormones( I have an upcoming post about this soon). Hormonal supplements should be taken according to dosage prescribed by a qualified medical practitioner. Do not self-prescribe. The medical practitioner can for &nbsp;example be &nbsp;a functional doctor. The supplements shrink the size and reduce inflammation and it&#8217;s not permanent.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Examples of Hormonal Supplements That Can Help</h2>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>&#8211; Chasteberry (Vitex)</li>
</ul>



<p>Balances estrogen and supports natural progesterone production. Helps with heavy periods, PMS, and fibroid-related hormonal imbalance.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>&#8211; DIM (Diindolylmethane)</li>
</ul>



<p>Aids the liver in breaking down excess estrogen. Supports healthy estrogen metabolism to slow fibroid growth.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>&#8211; Milk Thistle (Silymarin)</li>
</ul>



<p>Strengthens liver detox pathways. Helps your body clear out hormonal buildup and inflammation.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>&#8211; Inositol (Myoinositol + D-Chiro)</li>
</ul>



<p>Balances insulin and blood sugar. Supports hormonal balance especially if you also have PCOS or weight gain.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>&#8211; Ashwagandha</li>
</ul>



<p>Reduces cortisol and stress-related hormonal imbalances. Supports adrenal health and restores hormonal rhythm.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>&#8211; Kanchanara Guggulu</li>
</ul>



<p>An Ayurvedic formula known for shrinking fibroids, cysts, and glandular swelling. Supports lymphatic drainage, thyroid function, and uterine health.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>&#8211; Vitamin D3</li>
</ul>



<p>Helps regulate cell growth and supports immune function. Deficiency in vitamin D is linked to a higher risk of fibroid development. Supplementing can support hormone balance and reduce inflammation.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Healthy Lifestyle and Reducing Exposure</h2>



<p>Another thing you can do to shrink the size is adopt a healthy lifestyle. This includes eating healthily, working out, and reducing exposure to synthetic estrogens. Use BPA-free plastics or glass products. Avoid using cosmetic products or processed foods. Basically, when you buy any product, check the ingredients and if you see many chemicals you don’t understand, opt for another. The less ingredients the better. Also, opt for natural soaps, shampoos, lotions, and oils. Stress management is also key. Sleep well, avoid toxicity in any area of your life. If your mental health is not good, seek help.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What About a Permanent Solution?</h2>



<p>If you are reading all this and you’re like okay, can we just have a permanent solution and for now the one that is available is hysterectomy. Complete removal of the uterus. In my opinion, this is extreme and also I do feel like&nbsp; the medicine field fails women in research and solutions because as you have seen the causes are hormones in our body that cause and promote growth, yet with research and years of this condition affecting a lot of Black women, the only solution the medical team has is to remove the uterus. I do believe this can even harm your body.</p>



<p>Other gynecologists go as far as advising you to get babies then hysterectomy and believe that the condition occurs because you refuse to get children and dare, I say the most who hold this belief are ahem men. So, what if a lady decides to be child-free or not ready to be a mother? Are you going to force her to have babies which comes with their own risks? Because pregnancy is a high-risk condition to the body. You can get even high blood pressure or lose your life. So how can this be a solution? The medicine field needs to do right by women to get better solutions for us because all these treatment plans come with high risk and not&nbsp; a cure. In an upcoming post I will share the gaps that exist in medicine for women who experience hormonal and uterine conditions.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Final Thoughts</h2>



<p>Living with fibroids is tough. The symptoms are real and can affect your daily life, and the treatment choices are not always clear or fair. But understanding your body and your options is a powerful first step. I hope this post gives you clarity and the strength to keep asking questions and choosing what’s best for you.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/fibroids/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cycle and Diet</title>
		<link>/cycle-and-diet/</link>
					<comments>/cycle-and-diet/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[HHormones]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 10:19:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Harmonious Hormones: Learn & Flow]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=312</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Hey girlie on this post I showed the various hormones that are at work in our bodies with each phase of our cycle, now the building and functioning blocks of these hormones come from our diet, cholesterol and amino acids build hormones then vitamins and minerals help in the functioning of the hormones i.e. they [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="940" height="788" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/food-diet-Facebook-Post.png" alt="" class="wp-image-313" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/food-diet-Facebook-Post.png 940w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/food-diet-Facebook-Post-300x251.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/food-diet-Facebook-Post-768x644.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 940px) 100vw, 940px" /></figure>



<p>Hey girlie on this <a href="/know-your-hormones/" data-type="post" data-id="285">post</a> I showed the various hormones that are at work in our bodies with each phase of our cycle, now the building and functioning blocks of these hormones come from our diet, cholesterol and amino acids build hormones then vitamins and minerals help in the functioning of the hormones i.e. they help enzymes do the work of creating and activating hormones. See below table summary for each hormone source and role it plays.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Nutrients That Support Hormone Health</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="724" height="1024" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/1-724x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-398" style="width:557px;height:auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/1-724x1024.png 724w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/1-212x300.png 212w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/1-768x1086.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/1-1086x1536.png 1086w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/1-1448x2048.png 1448w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/1.png 1587w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 724px) 100vw, 724px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="724" height="1024" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/2-724x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-400" style="width:561px;height:auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/2-724x1024.png 724w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/2-212x300.png 212w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/2-768x1086.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/2-1086x1536.png 1086w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/2-1448x2048.png 1448w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/2.png 1587w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 724px) 100vw, 724px" /></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Energy Levels and Food in Each Cycle Phase</h3>



<p>So, from the above table the nutrients listed are to be considered in your diet. Another things is the energy levels in our cycle phases, on this <a href="/cycle-and-workouts/" data-type="post" data-id="307">post </a>I have explained in depth the energy levels in each cycle phase so in the phases where your energy is low you need to boost this with carbohydrates and girl I don’t mean go ham in burgers and fries I mean healthy carbohydrates. If you notice during luteal and menstrual phases we tend to have craving personally I crave cakes sweets and KFC so my body is signaling for high energy giving foods and during follicular and ovulation phase we have high energy this is where you focus on protein intake because your are the most active with workouts and activities you are busy as a bee these are high energy days.</p>



<p>Don’t get me wrong both proteins and carbohydrates are required in all phases do not say I won’t take proteins because I am in luteal no, take all the nutrients but be aware what your body needs more in each phase also let’s not forget mineral and vitamins this is from vegetables and fruits take this daily. You need fiber too for proper gut health and probiotics for healthy bacteria..</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The Gut–Hormone Connection<br></h3>



<p>Gut health is really, and I can’t stress this enough crucial for our hormones. Our gut is the control center. below I have shown how gut health connects to hormones</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table is-style-stripes"><table class="has-fixed-layout"><thead><tr><td><strong>Gut Role</strong></td><td><strong>What It Does for Hormones</strong></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><strong>Estrogen Detox (Estrobolome)</strong></td><td>Your gut has specific bacteria (called the <em>estrobolome</em>) that help break down and remove excess estrogen. If your gut is unhealthy or constipated, estrogen can get <strong>reabsorbed</strong>, leading to <strong>estrogen dominance</strong> (hello, fibroids, PMS, breast tenderness).</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Nutrient Absorption</strong></td><td>A healthy gut absorbs vitamins and minerals. Poor gut = poor absorption = hormone imbalance.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Cortisol + Stress Connection</strong></td><td>Your gut and brain are connected by the <strong>gut-brain axis</strong>. If your gut is inflamed, it can send stress signals to your brain, increasing <strong>cortisol</strong> (your stress hormone). High cortisol throws off your cycle, sleep, and fertility.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Mood + Serotonin</strong></td><td>Around <strong>90% of serotonin</strong> (your feel-good hormone) is made in your gut. So gut issues can lead to mood swings, anxiety, or PMS-related depression.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Inflammation + Hormonal Disorders</strong></td><td>Gut inflammation can trigger or worsen conditions like <strong>PCOS, endometriosis</strong>, and thyroid problems. An imbalanced gut creates <strong>chronic inflammation</strong>, which disrupts hormone communication.</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Hydration and the Liver<br></h3>



<p>Let us not forget hydration is crucial for your gut. Your water intake should be amazing, and I recommend the classic two liters per day. Excess sugar and processed food harm the gut flora</p>



<p>the liver is also crucial because it detoxes excess hormones like estrogen. If it becomes sluggish, especially from processed foods, stress, or alcohol, these hormones can build up and cause PMS, bloating, fatigue, and mood swings.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Alcohol and Hormones<br></h3>



<p>When it comes to alcohol, I know someone who drinks will not want to hear this, but alcohol is genereaally not good for the gut and liver and the brain chemicals because it disrupts the serotine and cortisol, wine is good for the gut but one too many isn’t . I also need you to be&nbsp; aware that during luteal and menstrual cycle alcohol can be&nbsp; a huge disruptor because it &nbsp;increases PMS coz, I have mentioned it affects cortisol and serotine and can increase cravings. When it comes to alcohol just reduce consumption and none is even better</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Enjoy Your Food: My Approach<br></h3>



<p>When you read all this, I am sure like this diet sounds restrictive and not enjoyable, but food should be enjoyed and not feel like a punishment . personally, for me what works is the Mediterranean diet. It hits all my nutrients spots and it’s enjoyable but what I would say is food depends on you and its personal so below I will give some sources of nutrients mentioned and pick what you like</p>



<p>also please keep in mind to not undereat when you trying to lose weight or over eat when you trying to gain , quantity of food is also essential</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/1-1-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-401" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/1-1-1024x576.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/1-1-300x169.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/1-1-768x432.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/1-1-1536x864.png 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/1-1.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/2-1-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-402" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/2-1-1024x576.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/2-1-300x169.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/2-1-768x432.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/2-1-1536x864.png 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/2-1.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>To also make it easier on what to put on your plate always think rainbow your meals should look like a rainbow where it has vegetables protein carbs and fruits see below the pic that can guide. </p>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="724" height="1024" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Colorful-Eat-the-Rainbow-Healthy-Diet-Poster-724x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-405" style="width:467px;height:auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Colorful-Eat-the-Rainbow-Healthy-Diet-Poster-724x1024.png 724w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Colorful-Eat-the-Rainbow-Healthy-Diet-Poster-212x300.png 212w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Colorful-Eat-the-Rainbow-Healthy-Diet-Poster-768x1086.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Colorful-Eat-the-Rainbow-Healthy-Diet-Poster-1086x1536.png 1086w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Colorful-Eat-the-Rainbow-Healthy-Diet-Poster-1448x2048.png 1448w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Colorful-Eat-the-Rainbow-Healthy-Diet-Poster.png 1587w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 724px) 100vw, 724px" /></figure>



<p>All in all hope this helps you in your diet journey and improves your body girlie</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/cycle-and-diet/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cycle and Workouts</title>
		<link>/cycle-and-workouts/</link>
					<comments>/cycle-and-workouts/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[HHormones]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 10:07:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Harmonious Hormones: Learn & Flow]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=307</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Lifestyle: working out Ladies we are always conditioned to workout thinking of calorie deficit, surplus or maintenance which is okay depending on your fitness goals. However, one thing that as women we should consider is our hormones. Hormones affect our energy levels in each phase of the cycle, so this post focuses on how to [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/fitness-1-1024x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-309" style="width:551px;height:auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/fitness-1-1024x1024.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/fitness-1-300x300.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/fitness-1-150x150.png 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/fitness-1-768x768.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/fitness-1.png 1080w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading">Lifestyle: working out</h1>



<p>Ladies we are always conditioned to workout thinking of calorie deficit, surplus or maintenance which is okay depending on your fitness goals. However, one thing that as women we should consider is our hormones. Hormones affect our energy levels in each phase of the cycle, so this post focuses on how to plan your workouts accordingly. From this post about the phases in our cycle (<a href="/know-your-hormones/" data-type="post" data-id="285">see link here</a>), I’ve explained in depth what hormones are at play in each phase and how this manifests in our bodies.<br>Each phase comes with its own energy levels because of the hormone changes, which is why it’s important to work out according to where your body is at.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Menstrual Phase: Sloth Mode (Go Slowest) </h2>



<p>Think sloth: slow, still, grounded. Go slowest.<br>Hormone levels are low. Both estrogen and progesterone drop here.<br>This is when your body is in pain, bleeding and your hormone levels are low so generally you are moody, tired and unmotivated. Do not feel the pressure to go hard in this phase because you are doing more harm than good to your body. When you are in the menstrual cycle prioritize low impact calming workouts. Go for a walk in nature or park, if you have a house with a compound walk barefoot to ground yourself, do yoga, pilates. It&#8217;s not the time to be increasing and lift weights of 50kgs, just light weights. Also girlie it&#8217;s not time to just do nothing. When you are in pain rest, but on the 3rd day to 5th when the flow is low prioritize gentle movement.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Follicular Phase: Bunny Mode (Step It Up)</h2>



<p>Think bunny: alert, energetic, playful. Step it up.<br>Estrogen is rising and brings energy and motivation.<br>The follicular phase is when estrogen levels start to rise and now you can go heavy with the weights that you are using. You can now focus on taking your workouts to the next level from gentle to strong. Best time for HIIT, resistance training and moderate cardio.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Ovulatory Phase: Gorilla Mode (Go Hardest)</h2>



<p>Think gorilla: strong, powerful, unstoppable. Go hardest.<br>Estrogen is high and testosterone may give a strength boost.<br>The ovulatory phase is when now with the hormones you are at your peak, the energy levels are the highest and this is when you can do the heaviest weights. Do more strength, the highest level of your workouts should be here. The body has greatest energy for movement so the hardest routines of your workout are best done here. Lift heaviest, stairmaster, hiking depending on which you find the most challenging.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Luteal Phase: Cat Mode (Slow It Down)</h2>



<p>Think cat: do not disturb, move at your own pace. Slow it down.<br>Progesterone is rising and your energy starts to dip.<br>The luteal phase is now the body is slowing down and your energy is beginning to go low. This is when you start slowing down and incorporating the low intensity classes: the yoga, pilates, barre. It’s the best time to do them. You can still include strength and cardio but not at your challenging levels but at your best. For example, you know you lift let’s say 50kg easy, you can maintain that or run at your highest speed. Basically no new challenging workouts but more of maintain as you slow down.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Final Thoughts</h2>



<p>With all these guidelines in mind I promise you your workouts will not affect your hormones. I have been there where I go to the gym then my period starts going irregular because the hormones are not taken into account when I workout. Your workouts and hormones should be a team, not against each other. So if you notice your cycle isn’t regular anymore or your hormones are imbalanced when you are working out (see how to tell from this <a href="/hormonal-imbalance/" data-type="post" data-id="301">post</a>), use the above guidelines in your workout routine to get them on track.<br>As you now know, working out without considering your diet is working hard, not smart. See this <a href="/cycle-and-diet/" data-type="post" data-id="312">post</a> also that gives a guide on hormones and diet. I have included an infographic to further illustrate workouts with the hormones</p>



<p><br>In conclusion, a good workout and good diet that keeps hormones in mind is the best thing for your body. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="712" height="637" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/cycle-workout-screenshot.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-310" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/cycle-workout-screenshot.jpg 712w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/cycle-workout-screenshot-300x268.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 712px) 100vw, 712px" /></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/cycle-and-workouts/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hormonal Imbalance</title>
		<link>/hormonal-imbalance/</link>
					<comments>/hormonal-imbalance/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[HHormones]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 09:39:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Harmonious Hormones: Learn & Flow]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=301</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What Is Hormonal Imbalance? So, hormonal imbalance is when your hormone levels are too high or too low during the cycle. Girlies, keep in mind each of our bodies is different, and learning your cycle patterns and listening to your body is a key thing for you to judge when things are right or wrong. [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized is-style-rounded"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="470" height="467" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/calendar-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-303" style="width:458px;height:auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/calendar-1.jpg 470w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/calendar-1-300x298.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/calendar-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 470px) 100vw, 470px" /></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What Is Hormonal Imbalance?</strong></h2>



<p>So, hormonal imbalance is when your hormone levels are too high or too low during the cycle. Girlies, keep in mind each of our bodies is different, and learning your cycle patterns and listening to your body is a key thing for you to judge when things are right or wrong.<br></p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What Causes Hormonal Imbalance?</strong></h3>



<p>Now, another thing you may be wondering is what could have caused the hormones to be imbalanced. The causes vary. One is a hormonal or uterine condition such as PCOS, fibroids, cysts, and endometriosis. These are often the result of hormonal imbalance rather than the root cause. For example, estrogen dominance contributes to fibroids and endometriosis. Ovarian cysts can result from hormonal issues like PCOS.</p>



<p>Other causes are chronic stress if you are going through a stressful time or a mental health condition, lack of sleep, wrong workout regime, poor diet, underlying conditions like diabetes or autoimmune diseases also play a role, and birth control too.<br></p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>How to Know Which Hormone Is Imbalanced</strong><br></h3>



<p>Ladies now how do you tell which hormone is imbalanced, the most accurate way is hormone testing in a medical facility. Note that this depends too on the day of the cycle. See the table below that gives you a good summary of the hormone tests.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Hormone Testing Summary</strong><br></h3>



<figure class="wp-block-table is-style-stripes"><table class="has-fixed-layout"><thead><tr><th><strong>Hormone</strong></th><th><strong>Best Day to Test</strong></th><th><strong>Test Type</strong></th><th><strong>Test Name (What to Ask For)</strong></th><th><strong>What It Reveals</strong></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><strong>Estradiol (E2)</strong></td><td>Cycle Day 3</td><td>Blood (serum)</td><td>“Estradiol blood test”</td><td>Baseline estrogen levels. High = estrogen dominance. Low = menopause, missed periods.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Progesterone</strong></td><td>~Day 21 (or 7 days after ovulation)</td><td>Blood (serum)</td><td>“Day 21 progesterone test”</td><td>Confirms ovulation. Low levels = PMS, spotting, infertility, anxiety.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>LH (Luteinizing Hormone)</strong></td><td>Cycle Day 3</td><td>Blood (serum)</td><td>“LH blood test”</td><td>High LH with high androgens may indicate PCOS. Supports ovulation assessment.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>FSH (Follicle-Stimulating Hormone)</strong></td><td>Cycle Day 3</td><td>Blood (serum)</td><td>“FSH blood test”</td><td>High = possible perimenopause or low ovarian reserve.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Testosterone (Free &amp; Total)</strong></td><td>Any day (morning preferred)</td><td>Blood (serum)</td><td>“Free and total testosterone test”</td><td>High levels = acne, facial hair, PCOS, low libido if too low.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>DHEA-S</strong></td><td>Any day</td><td>Blood (serum)</td><td>“DHEA-S test”</td><td>Measures adrenal hormone production. High = possible androgen excess.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Cortisol</strong></td><td>8–9 AM for blood; or full-day saliva</td><td>Blood / Saliva / Urine (DUTCH test)</td><td>“AM cortisol” or “4-point saliva cortisol test”</td><td>High = chronic stress. Low = burnout or adrenal fatigue.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Thyroid Panel (TSH, Free T3, Free T4)</strong></td><td>Any day</td><td>Blood (serum)</td><td>“Thyroid function panel”</td><td>Checks for hypothyroidism or hyperthyroidism. Affects energy, cycle, mood, weight.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Prolactin</strong></td><td>Any day (morning, fasting optional)</td><td>Blood (serum)</td><td>“Prolactin test”</td><td>High levels can suppress ovulation and cause missed or irregular periods.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Insulin + Glucose</strong></td><td>Fasting, any day</td><td>Blood (serum)</td><td>“Fasting insulin and glucose”</td><td>Insulin resistance (common in PCOS). Blood sugar imbalance impacts all hormones.</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Symptoms of Hormonal Imbalance</h3>



<p>For the symptoms, they usually don’t appear alone. It happens in clusters that form consistent patterns. Also, you can experience imbalances in more than one hormone, for example, low progesterone and high estrogen during chronic stress or a sluggish liver. See below symptoms and what it is likely the cause hormone</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Hormonal Symptoms Breakdown</h3>



<figure class="wp-block-table is-style-stripes"><table class="has-fixed-layout"><thead><tr><th><strong>Hormone</strong></th><th><strong>When It’s Likely Low</strong></th><th><strong>When It’s Likely High</strong></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><strong>Estrogen</strong></td><td>&#8211; Missed periods or very light flow<br>&#8211; Vaginal dryness<br>&#8211; Hot flashes / night sweats<br>&#8211; Low libido<br>&#8211; Sadness, apathy<br>&#8211; Poor memory or brain fog</td><td>&#8211; Heavy/prolonged periods<br>&#8211; Breast tenderness- Bloating<br>&#8211; PMS mood swings<br>&#8211; Fibroids or endometriosis symptoms<br>&#8211; Fat gain on hips/thighs</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Progesterone</strong></td><td>&#8211; Anxiety or restlessness (especially pre-period)<br>&#8211; Insomnia<br>&#8211; Spotting before period<br>&#8211; Short cycles (&lt;25 days)<br>&#8211; PMS or breast tenderness<br>&#8211; Early miscarriages</td><td>&#8211; Excessive sleepiness or fatigue<br>&#8211; Dizziness<br>&#8211; Bloating<br>&#8211; Depressed mood or fogginess<br><em>(Rare; excess progesterone usually only occurs with certain medications or hormone therapy)</em></td></tr><tr><td><strong>FSH (Follicle-Stimulating Hormone)</strong></td><td>&#8211; Low ovarian reserve or irregular ovulation (often silent without testing)<br>&#8211; Early menopause signs (hot flashes, low libido)</td><td>&#8211; Hot flashes before menopause<br>&#8211; Fertility challenges<br>&#8211; Skipped periods<br>&#8211; Dryness or vaginal thinning</td></tr><tr><td><strong>LH (Luteinizing Hormone)</strong></td><td>&#8211; Weak ovulation or anovulation (can show as irregular or long cycles)<br>&#8211; Low libido</td><td>&#8211; Irregular or absent periods<br>&#8211; PCOS symptoms <br>&#8211; Mid-cycle spotting or cramping</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Testosterone</strong></td><td>&#8211; Low libido<br>&#8211; Low motivation<br>&#8211; Poor muscle tone<br>&#8211; Fatigue<br>&#8211; Mood instability</td><td>&#8211; Acne (especially jawline/chin)<br>&#8211; Facial/body hair growth<br>&#8211; Scalp hair thinning<br>&#8211; Anger or aggression<br>&#8211; Irregular cycles (common in PCOS)</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Cortisol</strong></td><td>&#8211; Fatigue despite rest<br>&#8211; Salt cravings<br>&#8211; Dizziness when standing<br>&#8211; Weakened stress response<br>&#8211; Low blood pressure</td><td>&#8211; Belly fat gain<br>&#8211; Sleep trouble<br>&#8211; Anxiety or “wired but tired” feeling<br>&#8211; Cravings for sugar or caffeine<br>&#8211; Hormonal acne</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Thyroid (Low T3/T4)</strong></td><td>&#8211; Fatigue<br>&#8211; Cold sensitivity<br>&#8211; Dry skin<br>&#8211; Constipation<br>&#8211; Irregular or heavy periods<br>&#8211; Depression<br>&#8211; <strong>Lumps or swelling at front of neck (possible goiter)</strong></td><td>&#8211; Sweating<br>&#8211; Fast heartbeat<br>&#8211; Anxiety<br>&#8211; Weight loss<br>&#8211; Light or missed periods<br>&#8211; Trembling hands<br>&#8211; Insomnia</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Insulin</strong></td><td>&#8211; Fatigue after meals<br>&#8211; Cravings for sweets or carbs<br>&#8211; Difficulty losing weight<br>&#8211; Irregular cycles<br>&#8211; Skin tags or dark patches on neck/armpits</td><td>&#8211; Same as low: High insulin (insulin resistance) often causes both fatigue and weight issues, especially in PCOS</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Prolactin</strong></td><td>&#8211; Missed periods<br>&#8211; Low libido<br>&#8211; Milk production without pregnancy<br>&#8211; Infertility<br>&#8211; Headaches or blurry vision</td><td>&#8211; Same — excess is the issue. High levels suppress ovulation and reduce estrogen/progesterone production</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What to Do About Hormonal Imbalance</strong><br></h3>



<p>Now we know the symptoms and causes. What’s next is what to do. The best way to keep your hormones balanced is through good gut health and a healthy lifestyle that includes a good workout and diet and sleep which is 8-9 hours. You can also check with your gynecologist which birth control they can recommend for you. Supplements are also an option to support hormonal balance when used correctly, and I’ll be covering those in a separate post. As for any underlying conditions, we will explore them one by one in upcoming posts</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">More Resources</h3>



<p>For a healthy lifestyle please see the links  on <a href="/cycle-and-diet/" data-type="post" data-id="312">diet </a>and <a href="/cycle-and-workouts/" data-type="post" data-id="307">workout</a>.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/hormonal-imbalance/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Know your Hormones&#8230;</title>
		<link>/know-your-hormones/</link>
					<comments>/know-your-hormones/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[HHormones]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 13:04:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Harmonious Hormones: Learn & Flow]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=285</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Periods: The Bane of Existence Periods, the bane of an existence for a woman. Nearly every woman has it. Before my experience with fibroids (see link here), I didn’t care much about it. TBH I had done my biology education and didn’t take time to fully understand my cycle and hormones, which now I do, [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-core-columns-is-layout-28f84493 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow" style="flex-basis:100%">
<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-default"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="345" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/menses-2-1-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-345" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/menses-2-1-1024x576.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/menses-2-1-300x169.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/menses-2-1-768x432.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/menses-2-1-1536x864.png 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/menses-2-1.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>
</figure>
</div>
</div>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Periods: The Bane of Existence</strong></h4>



<p>Periods, the bane of an existence for a woman. Nearly every woman has it. Before my experience with fibroids (<a href="/fibroids/" data-type="post" data-id="318">see link here)</a>, I didn’t care much about it. TBH I had done my biology education and didn’t take time to fully understand my cycle and hormones, which now I do, and passing this knowledge to you coz it’s essential you learn how your body is functioning in every phase of your cycle and what hormones are at play.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Understanding a Regular vs. Irregular Period</strong></h4>



<p>Ladies, the cycle is really how you get an inclining of how your hormones are balanced or imbalanced and what that means for your body. Typically, a woman in a balanced cycle should be between 21 to 35 days, have a flow for 4 to 7 days, and cramps that can be managed by a painkiller at low dosage. The blood flow varies, heavy at first and it subsides to the last day, and also the product you use (a tampon, pad, or menstrual cup) has frequency to it, but the average range is 3 to 5 hours.</p>



<p>So this is a regular cycle. Now, anything outside this is an irregular cycle. So girlies, having a period that’s so heavy and you soak your product in under three hours isn’t normal. Having cramps so painful you need high dosage painkillers, not normal. Heavy clots, not it. Having a period greater than 7 days is a no. All these point to irregular periods and this means your hormones aren’t balanced and they need your attention. I have covered here hormonal imbalance and irregular cycles <a href="/hormonal-imbalance/" data-type="post" data-id="301">here</a>.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The Main Hormones in Our Cycle</strong></h4>



<p><strong><em>Estrogen aka the builder</em>:</strong> this is what thickens our uterine lining and supports egg maturation, also improves the mood, energy, libido and skin</p>



<p><strong><em>Progesterone aka the calmer</em>:</strong> maintains uterine lining after ovulation and supports early pregnancy, calms nervous system and balances the mood</p>



<p><strong><em>LH (Luteinizing Hormone) aka the releaser</em>:</strong> triggers egg release</p>



<p><strong><em>FSH (Follicle Stimulating Hormone) aka the grower</em>:</strong> stimulates follicles in the eggs to mature in the ovaries</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Neurotransmitters aka Brain Chemicals</strong></h4>



<p><strong><em>Serotonin aka the stabilizer</em>:</strong> keeps your mood, sleep and emotions balanced</p>



<p><strong><em>Dopamine aka the motivator</em>:</strong> fuels focus, ambition, motivation and excitement, the I can do anything guy maybe girl, I see it as a girl or what do you think</p>



<p><strong><em>Oxytocin aka the connector</em>:</strong> the love hormone, need I say here we have trust, empathy and bonding</p>



<p><strong><em>Cortisol aka the alarm bell</em>:</strong> it does keep you alert in stress but when too much is what causes the stress coz it makes you overwhelmed and anxious</p>



<p><strong><em>GABA the soother</em>:</strong> emotion regulation, this one calms your nervous system and deep rest</p>



<p>So, note that estrogen stimulates the levels of serotonin in the body and progesterone stimulates GABA activity. Serotonin increases as estrogen increases and falls when estrogen levels decline. Likewise, GABA increases as progesterone rises and drops when progesterone declines.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The Menstrual Phase</strong></h4>



<p>Shark week if you know, the days we dread. Basically, this is where we have the actual bleeding, the lining of your uterus is being shed and it comes with a lot. Also, this is the beginning of your cycle so here most hormones are low, that’s why you go through so much moodiness and stress. Estrogen and progesterone are low here, the brain chemicals are low except for the cortisol. FSH begins to rise slightly this phase.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The Follicular Phase</strong></h4>



<p>So next is follicular stage. Basically, the ovaries are preparing the egg, days 1 to 20 depending on your cycle length. Estrogen and FSH rise, LH is slowly rising, and progesterone still low. Serotonin increases, dopamine is rising while cortisol is lowering, the GABA is still low. This phase, prioritize strategy, goal setting, creating etc.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Ovulation Phase</strong></h4>



<p>Everyone’s fav, we in the middle cycle, day depends with the cycle length but it usually happens in the 14th to 21st day. Yes, it&#8217;s only one day. Estrogen is at its peak, LH surges, FSH begins to drop as the egg is now being released for fertilization. And for the brain chemicals, the serotonin peaks too, dopamine peaks too, oxytocin is high, cortisol is low to normal and GABA is low. See why she is the favorite girl? Now you are at your peak confidence so I would tell you, the project you have been meaning to start, do it then, or any other thing you have been afraid to do including the hard convos, do it on this day.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The Luteal Phase</strong></h4>



<p>This happens on day 15 to 28, as said before depending on the cycle. The body prepares for pregnancy and if none is happening, we are given our greatest jail sentence for life, the period. So here, the progesterone and estrogen rise to prepare for pregnancy then drop when there is no fertilized egg. LH and FSH drop. For our brain chemicals, the serotonin drops in late luteal, dopamine drops too, oxytocin drops near PMS, and cortisol can rise. GABA rises then drops before period. Here is where PMS is triggered. So please, no stress, prioritize sleep, basically go slow mode girl.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Final Thoughts: Track and Live With Your Cycle</strong></h4>



<p>I hope this deep dive helps. All these will happen when one has a regular cycle. So as you track your cycle on your fav app, please keep in mind which phase you are at and what is happening to your body because of the hormone levels. And here is the good thing, you can create a lifestyle depending on your cycle phase. I have covered it more on this post. So this lifestyle includes <a href="/cycle-and-diet/" data-type="post" data-id="312">diet</a>, <a href="/cycle-and-workouts/" data-type="post" data-id="307">how to workout</a>, and what to do in terms of your goals.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1080" height="1080" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/cycle-infographic-1.png" alt="" class="wp-image-330" style="width:526px;height:auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/cycle-infographic-1.png 1080w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/cycle-infographic-1-300x300.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/cycle-infographic-1-1024x1024.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/cycle-infographic-1-150x150.png 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/07/cycle-infographic-1-768x768.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1080px) 100vw, 1080px" /></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/know-your-hormones/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>My  Story&#8230;..</title>
		<link>/my-story/</link>
					<comments>/my-story/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[HHormones]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 11:56:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Harmonious Voices]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=107</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[From Emergency Surgery to Starting This Blog Fibroids run in my family. My mum has them and is still managing them to this day. My aunt had them too &#160;and later had a hysterectomy and developed breast cancer. I haven’t seen any proven medical connection between fibroids and breast cancer, but it made me start [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="has-text-align-center is-style-text-annotation has-large-font-size is-style-text-annotation--3"><strong><em>From Emergency Surgery to Starting This Blog</em></strong></p>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image aligncenter size-full is-resized is-style-rounded wp-duotone-unset-4" style="margin-top:0;margin-bottom:0"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="512" height="512" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/cropped-self-love.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-11" style="width:352px;height:auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/cropped-self-love.jpg 512w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/06/cropped-self-love-300x300.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/06/cropped-self-love-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" /></figure>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Fibroids run in my family. My mum has them and is still managing them to this day. My aunt had them too &nbsp;and later had a hysterectomy and developed breast cancer. I haven’t seen any proven medical connection between fibroids and breast cancer, but it made me start wondering just how much our hormones influence our overall health. That experience pushed me to start asking more questions &nbsp;about fibroids, about hormone balance, and about the lack of clear research in women’s reproductive health.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">So, when I was diagnosed in 2022, I wasn’t exactly shocked. My belly had been growing; it looked like I was five months pregnant. But I thought: <em>&#8220;I know people who live with fibroids. I’ll be fine.&#8221;</em></p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">The OB/GYN said to me &nbsp;<em>“You can’t just bury your head in the sand and ignore a problem expecting it to just go away,”</em> &nbsp;that was my warning bell</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">I walked out of that clinic with a birth control prescription ikr, right? Don’t judge me A whole fibroids diagnosis and we’re talking about birth control? Later we will explore the effects of this on our hormones overall</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">I didn’t do anything about this diagnosis and &nbsp;about a year later…</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">One random afternoon, I was at the mall, shopping, running errands. Suddenly, a sharp pain hit the side of my stomach. I sat down. “It’s just my period,” I told myself. “I haven’t eaten. Let me take some tea and a muffin and I’ll be fine.”</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">But the pain didn’t go away. It eased up a bit, but lingered. I pushed through the day anyway.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Later that night, the pain got way worse, I couldn’t move properly. I was vomiting green bile. Couldn’t eat. Couldn’t even take a sip of water. I thought, <em>Maybe it’s acidity?</em> I tried antacids, baking soda, and all the homemade tricks. Nothing worked. I couldn’t sleep. The pain was becoming unbearable.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Morning came. I told my sister I am not moving at all she had been receiving updates on my health throughout the night also her she thought that’s just cramps from the periods or bloating</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Within 20 minutes, my family was at my door. They carried me to the car and rushed me to the emergency room.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>Diagnosis: fibroids. Emergency surgery.</strong></p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">The fibroids had grown so large they were pressing on my colon</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">It was traumatic. I kept thinking: <em>People live with fibroids. Why do I have to go through surgery?</em> But it had to be done.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">That surgery changed me. I was alone. I was scared. I was going through a rough patch in life, wheeled into an operating room. And when I came out, the OB/GYN told me:</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>“You need to have a baby within two years, or you’ll need a hysterectomy.”</strong></p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Let that sink in.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">At that point, I had no partner, I wasn’t even sure I wanted kids. And now, apparently, having a baby was the “cure”?</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">That moment became the turning point for me.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">I spent the next two years on a journey &nbsp;where I had taken on learning my body, researching, and changing my lifestyle. I adjusted my diet. I took supplements. I prioritized sleep and even changed careers roles, Why? Because I refused to go through that pain again.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">And <strong>that</strong> is why I started this blog.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">To share what I’ve learned.<br>To be a voice for the women who are confused, dismissed, overwhelmed.<br>To create a space where we can talk about fibroids, hormones, pain, surgery, fertility, emotions and more</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">You&#8217;re not alone. If you&#8217;re navigating this journey, I see you. I’ve been there.<br>And I’ll be sharing everything I’ve learned &nbsp;including how to manage your hormones, track your cycle, and take charge of your health.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>This is just the beginning.</strong></p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Stick around. Let’s walk along this path together.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><em>And yes, that emergency surgery? It wasn’t the last. I later had to go through another operation due to an adhesion a story I’ll share in an upcoming post.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/my-story/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
