<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Harmonious Voices &#8211; Harmonious-Hormones</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/real-stories-shared-journeys/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 16:27:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>My  Story&#8230;..</title>
		<link>/my-story/</link>
					<comments>/my-story/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[HHormones]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 11:56:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Harmonious Voices]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=107</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[From Emergency Surgery to Starting This Blog Fibroids run in my family. My mum has them and is still managing them to this day. My aunt had them too &#160;and later had a hysterectomy and developed breast cancer. I haven’t seen any proven medical connection between fibroids and breast cancer, but it made me start [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="has-text-align-center is-style-text-annotation has-large-font-size is-style-text-annotation--2"><strong><em>From Emergency Surgery to Starting This Blog</em></strong></p>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image aligncenter size-full is-resized is-style-rounded wp-duotone-unset-3" style="margin-top:0;margin-bottom:0"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="512" height="512" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/cropped-self-love.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-11" style="width:352px;height:auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/cropped-self-love.jpg 512w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/06/cropped-self-love-300x300.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/06/cropped-self-love-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" /></figure>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Fibroids run in my family. My mum has them and is still managing them to this day. My aunt had them too &nbsp;and later had a hysterectomy and developed breast cancer. I haven’t seen any proven medical connection between fibroids and breast cancer, but it made me start wondering just how much our hormones influence our overall health. That experience pushed me to start asking more questions &nbsp;about fibroids, about hormone balance, and about the lack of clear research in women’s reproductive health.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">So, when I was diagnosed in 2022, I wasn’t exactly shocked. My belly had been growing; it looked like I was five months pregnant. But I thought: <em>&#8220;I know people who live with fibroids. I’ll be fine.&#8221;</em></p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">The OB/GYN said to me &nbsp;<em>“You can’t just bury your head in the sand and ignore a problem expecting it to just go away,”</em> &nbsp;that was my warning bell</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">I walked out of that clinic with a birth control prescription ikr, right? Don’t judge me A whole fibroids diagnosis and we’re talking about birth control? Later we will explore the effects of this on our hormones overall</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">I didn’t do anything about this diagnosis and &nbsp;about a year later…</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">One random afternoon, I was at the mall, shopping, running errands. Suddenly, a sharp pain hit the side of my stomach. I sat down. “It’s just my period,” I told myself. “I haven’t eaten. Let me take some tea and a muffin and I’ll be fine.”</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">But the pain didn’t go away. It eased up a bit, but lingered. I pushed through the day anyway.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Later that night, the pain got way worse, I couldn’t move properly. I was vomiting green bile. Couldn’t eat. Couldn’t even take a sip of water. I thought, <em>Maybe it’s acidity?</em> I tried antacids, baking soda, and all the homemade tricks. Nothing worked. I couldn’t sleep. The pain was becoming unbearable.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Morning came. I told my sister I am not moving at all she had been receiving updates on my health throughout the night also her she thought that’s just cramps from the periods or bloating</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Within 20 minutes, my family was at my door. They carried me to the car and rushed me to the emergency room.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>Diagnosis: fibroids. Emergency surgery.</strong></p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">The fibroids had grown so large they were pressing on my colon</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">It was traumatic. I kept thinking: <em>People live with fibroids. Why do I have to go through surgery?</em> But it had to be done.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">That surgery changed me. I was alone. I was scared. I was going through a rough patch in life, wheeled into an operating room. And when I came out, the OB/GYN told me:</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>“You need to have a baby within two years, or you’ll need a hysterectomy.”</strong></p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Let that sink in.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">At that point, I had no partner, I wasn’t even sure I wanted kids. And now, apparently, having a baby was the “cure”?</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">That moment became the turning point for me.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">I spent the next two years on a journey &nbsp;where I had taken on learning my body, researching, and changing my lifestyle. I adjusted my diet. I took supplements. I prioritized sleep and even changed careers roles, Why? Because I refused to go through that pain again.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">And <strong>that</strong> is why I started this blog.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">To share what I’ve learned.<br>To be a voice for the women who are confused, dismissed, overwhelmed.<br>To create a space where we can talk about fibroids, hormones, pain, surgery, fertility, emotions and more</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">You&#8217;re not alone. If you&#8217;re navigating this journey, I see you. I’ve been there.<br>And I’ll be sharing everything I’ve learned &nbsp;including how to manage your hormones, track your cycle, and take charge of your health.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>This is just the beginning.</strong></p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Stick around. Let’s walk along this path together.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><em>And yes, that emergency surgery? It wasn’t the last. I later had to go through another operation due to an adhesion a story I’ll share in an upcoming post.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/my-story/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
