<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Harmonious Voices &#8211; Harmonious-Hormones</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/real-stories-shared-journeys/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 10:53:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Her Story&#8230; PCOS Journey</title>
		<link>/her-story-pcos-journey/</link>
					<comments>/her-story-pcos-journey/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[HHormones]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 14:22:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Harmonious Voices]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PCOS]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=534</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Introduction / Background I am a 23 year old, Just started my professional journey after campus and got recently diagnosed with PCOS. In terms of working out I have been semi active , I did take walks when necessary and had periods of intense workouts. I wasn&#8217;t going to the gym and had a lot [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized is-style-rounded"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1080" height="1080" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Her-PCOS-story.png" alt="" class="wp-image-539" style="aspect-ratio:4/3;object-fit:contain;width:375px;height:auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Her-PCOS-story.png 1080w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Her-PCOS-story-300x300.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Her-PCOS-story-1024x1024.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Her-PCOS-story-150x150.png 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Her-PCOS-story-768x768.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1080px) 100vw, 1080px" /></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Introduction / Background</h3>



<p>I am a 23 year old, Just started my professional journey after campus and got recently diagnosed with PCOS. In terms of  working out I have been semi active , I did take walks when necessary and had periods of intense workouts. I wasn&#8217;t going to the gym and had a lot of wheat in my diet. I noticed something was wrong with my health when I had depression and anxiety ,I was taking prescribed medication for my mental health and then my periods became irregular. It started coming after 40 days and took a huge node dive to 60 days and sometimes not come at all . After I completed my degree I started being passive about my health for example I stopped working out ,started drinking more and I gained weight. My period became more irregular coming after 60 days or not coming at all. I assumed it was an issue with one of my ovaries because I could feel pain during ovulation</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Symptoms</h3>



<p>As mentioned I had really irregular periods ,I went on a deep dive in the internet to search ways of making the period come faster like eating paw paw seeds, drinking turmeric ginger concoctions and I did a lot of pregnancy tests thinking I might be pregnant. When I heard of PCOS it was girlies getting heavy periods with a lot of cramping mine wasn&#8217;t, but it became worse with time though I could survive with pain killers and I read that the girls also had non existent periods for three months and mine was just hitting the sixty days mark, I had heavy moody swings like having teenage anger that is irrational. </p>



<p>I decided to go to a gynaecologists, more than one , they did scans and nothing was found just fibroids which were microscopic. I started having spotting to kinda bleeding before my period and I would brush it off as ovulation. When I confided in someone they would say its normal, I just felt the support I had around me wasn&#8217;t the best because everyone was just brushing it off as normal stress because I had anxiety , diet  and  working out too much. I felt like nobody was seeing the gravity of the situation so long as I am not pregnant my circle just didn&#8217;t have the knowledge and seriousness to assess that something was wrong in my body</p>



<p>Earlier this year things took the turn for the worse in March I bled for like an entire month. The first two weeks it was spotting and I just brushed it off like normal things that happens in my cycle. The next two weeks that followed the bleeding got heavy like I am on my period so I asked my mum to see a gynaecologist and she was like give it time it will end . I started feeling dizzy and if it wasn&#8217;t someone close pushing me to go to the hospital I wouldn&#8217;t have taken the matter seriously.</p>



<p>In my gynaecologist appointment she evaluated my symptoms and did a scan and there we saw my ovaries were inflamed hence the PCOS diagnosis. Another thing she pointed out my acne, I did take good care of my skin but I still had them. If I didn&#8217;t have a good sleep of 6-8 hours and if I ate too much sugar acne would pop up .I had a bad gut health and I was thinking it was a result of H-pylori diagnosis but I did all the right things ate vegetables, consumed chia seeds, did natural juices ,kombucha &amp; kimchi but my gut health didn&#8217;t improve.</p>



<p>Every month was just overwhelming for me with my cycle: I was worried my period was coming late, I had hormonal acne ,my gut is a mess .I even forgot how to be normal ,things like having normal sleep, eat what I wanted and not have any gut issues and having no acne after using the correct skin care steps were just non existent in my day to day.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Path to Diagnosis</h3>



<p>I went to see a doctor and during the appointment is when I realized the gravity of hormonal conditions like it affects every aspect of my health (mental, physical, gut, face). It was draining doing the right things drinking water, working out, eating healthy and I am still not getting better</p>



<p>The doctor did a hormonal test and it showed my progesterone was low. She put me on medicine for a month and the bleeding stopped after three days.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Emotions</h3>



<p>On hearing the PCOS diagnosis I cried and all the internet information I start researching was a lot, seeing that you can get cancer, diabetes and be infertile the fact that it had no cure was another thing ,Chatgpt saying sorry that I have a chronic condition. I was really scared and thought I am too young to be going through this but there was a part of me that had relief to know what was going on in my body.</p>



<p>My doctor suggested I stop eating wheat and diary . It was hard because wheat is my staple food anyone who knows me will tell you I love bread so I searched on the different diets I could adopt and I just got hopeless because everyone had their own conflicting opinion on what I should do and not do.</p>



<p>Researching the causes  was also another world  it could be a stressful environments yet I am a naturally anxious individual and now I am starting to think also maybe my anxiety is caused by PCOS  who knows? Is it my gut? I start to overthink how I need to change my lifestyle yet I am still so young only 23 am I infertile? I was just really questioning everything.</p>



<p>I started even thinking of how many women go through this and don&#8217;t have an answer. When I had googled my symptoms before the doctor&#8217;s appointment , I got all manner of diagnosis like ovarian cancer , Gut issues , others did say PCOS but I just got overwhelmed with information. I bottled up all my emotions and shut down the symptoms I was experiencing because I thought I am not as badly off as long as after sixty days I had my period and it was coming for five days.</p>



<p> I didn&#8217;t realize the magnitude of it until my recent appointment what held me back was that fear of something chronic. I did feel like it was a bit unfair to be having this condition especially since my lifestyle was the same as any young woman in my age range like with my friends we all had the same routine of school, work, went to the parties and be semi active but I am the one stuck with this condition. I kept looking back what could be done differently but I realized I cant blame myself and I may never know the root causes coz they vary and they are many.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Interaction with Doctors &amp; Healthcare System</h3>



<p>The doctor who gave me my diagnosis was a woman and before this I had three checkups with male gynaecologists and all of the male ones were very dismissive of my concerns on why my period wasn&#8217;t regular. My doctor took time to listen to me and diagnose me properly. She gave me attention and time that I needed considering my appointment was just slotted during her lunch hour break.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Treatment / Recommendations</h3>



<p>My doctor was opposed to birth control, she prescribed me medicine to mitigate the condition and to try to  reset my body to a balanced hormone level. Before the prescription she made sure I changed my diet to no dairy and wheat and my body improved . On top of this I cut down on my alcohol intake. My gut got better than before , I find it easier to lose weight I did a lot of walks within the week covering my ten k steps nothing strenuous. I am still on the path of the treatment taking a day at a time.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Advice &amp; Words for Others:</h3>



<p>I am still on my treatment plan and I have decided to also personally take a mental note of how things in my environment affect me for example what  I and how my body reacts to certain foods , does my job stress me out, does a certain person affect my mental health if so I cut them off. </p>



<p>People need to be aware how our reproductive system affects our daily lives in terms of mood, gut, hormones , mental health its all connected and if one thing is a miss it has a way of affecting all other things. I advocate for checkups especially when you notice something out of the norm and find a doctor that listens.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Closing:</h3>



<p>I am hopeful for good things and I am positive that my cycle will reset and the condition isn&#8217;t as threatening I am doing okay and I feel way lighter , I am giving it a year and will update you around this time next year on how I am doing.</p>



<p>I hope this posts helps you especially if you have the same condition and have a similar journey you are not alone and you will overcome. </p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p>To get more information on PCOS see this <a href="/pcos/" data-type="post" data-id="573">post </a>which discusses what PCOS is and causes in great detail, <a href="/pcos-diet/" data-type="post" data-id="588">this </a>one breaks down the diet.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/her-story-pcos-journey/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>My  Story&#8230;..</title>
		<link>/my-story/</link>
					<comments>/my-story/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[HHormones]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 11:56:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Fibroids]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harmonious Voices]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=107</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[From Emergency Surgery to Starting This Blog Fibroids run in my family. My mum has them and is still managing them to this day. My aunt had them too &#160;and later had a hysterectomy and developed breast cancer. I haven’t seen any proven medical connection between fibroids and breast cancer, but it made me start [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="has-text-align-center is-style-text-annotation has-large-font-size is-style-text-annotation--2"><strong><em>From Emergency Surgery to Starting This Blog</em></strong></p>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image aligncenter size-full is-resized is-style-rounded wp-duotone-unset-3" style="margin-top:0;margin-bottom:0"><img decoding="async" width="512" height="512" src="/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/cropped-self-love.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-11" style="width:352px;height:auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/cropped-self-love.jpg 512w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/06/cropped-self-love-300x300.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2025/06/cropped-self-love-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" /></figure>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Fibroids run in my family. My mum has them and is still managing them to this day. My aunt had them too &nbsp;and later had a hysterectomy and developed breast cancer. I haven’t seen any proven medical connection between fibroids and breast cancer, but it made me start wondering just how much our hormones influence our overall health. That experience pushed me to start asking more questions &nbsp;about fibroids, about hormone balance, and about the lack of clear research in women’s reproductive health.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">So, when I was diagnosed in 2022, I wasn’t exactly shocked. My belly had been growing; it looked like I was five months pregnant. But I thought: <em>&#8220;I know people who live with fibroids. I’ll be fine.&#8221;</em></p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">The OB/GYN said to me &nbsp;<em>“You can’t just bury your head in the sand and ignore a problem expecting it to just go away,”</em> &nbsp;that was my warning bell</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">I walked out of that clinic with a birth control prescription ikr, right? Don’t judge me A whole fibroids diagnosis and we’re talking about birth control? Later we will explore the effects of this on our hormones overall</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">I didn’t do anything about this diagnosis and &nbsp;about a year later…</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">One random afternoon, I was at the mall, shopping, running errands. Suddenly, a sharp pain hit the side of my stomach. I sat down. “It’s just my period,” I told myself. “I haven’t eaten. Let me take some tea and a muffin and I’ll be fine.”</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">But the pain didn’t go away. It eased up a bit, but lingered. I pushed through the day anyway.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Later that night, the pain got way worse, I couldn’t move properly. I was vomiting green bile. Couldn’t eat. Couldn’t even take a sip of water. I thought, <em>Maybe it’s acidity?</em> I tried antacids, baking soda, and all the homemade tricks. Nothing worked. I couldn’t sleep. The pain was becoming unbearable.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Morning came. I told my sister I am not moving at all she had been receiving updates on my health throughout the night also her she thought that’s just cramps from the periods or bloating</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Within 20 minutes, my family was at my door. They carried me to the car and rushed me to the emergency room.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>Diagnosis: fibroids. Emergency surgery.</strong></p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">The fibroids had grown so large they were pressing on my colon</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">It was traumatic. I kept thinking: <em>People live with fibroids. Why do I have to go through surgery?</em> But it had to be done.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">That surgery changed me. I was alone. I was scared. I was going through a rough patch in life, wheeled into an operating room. And when I came out, the OB/GYN told me:</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>“You need to have a baby within two years, or you’ll need a hysterectomy.”</strong></p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Let that sink in.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">At that point, I had no partner, I wasn’t even sure I wanted kids. And now, apparently, having a baby was the “cure”?</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">That moment became the turning point for me.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">I spent the next two years on a journey &nbsp;where I had taken on learning my body, researching, and changing my lifestyle. I adjusted my diet. I took supplements. I prioritized sleep and even changed careers roles, Why? Because I refused to go through that pain again.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">And <strong>that</strong> is why I started this blog.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">To share what I’ve learned.<br>To be a voice for the women who are confused, dismissed, overwhelmed.<br>To create a space where we can talk about fibroids, hormones, pain, surgery, fertility, emotions and more</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">You&#8217;re not alone. If you&#8217;re navigating this journey, I see you. I’ve been there.<br>And I’ll be sharing everything I’ve learned &nbsp;including how to manage your hormones, track your cycle, and take charge of your health.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>This is just the beginning.</strong></p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">Stick around. Let’s walk along this path together.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><em>And yes, that emergency surgery? It wasn’t the last. I later had to go through another operation due to an adhesion a story I’ll share in an upcoming post.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/my-story/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
